A Guide to the Lyman Chalkley Papers, 1816-1922 (bulk 1890-1903)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Lyman Chalkley Papers, 1816-1922 (bulk 1890-1903)
The Library of Virginia
51713
5.4 cubic feet (12 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Augusta County Circuit Court, Staunton.
Biographical Information
Lyman Chalkley was born in Richmond, Virginia on 20 October 1861. He was the son of Otway Hebron Chalkley (1830-1883) and Susan Marian Jordan (1838-1889). Chalkley attended Richmond College, the University of Virginia, Columbia College, and Berlin Univeristy. He received his law degree from Washington and Lee University in 1889. On 27 June 1889 he married Eleanor Desha Breckinridge (1862-1943) of Lexington, Kentucky. She was the daughter of Rep. William Campbell Preston Breckinridge (1837-1904) and Issa Desha (1843-1892). They settled in Covington, Virginia, where Chalkley practiced law. In 1891, he was elected judge of the district of Alleghany and Craig Counties, and served for six years. From 1898 to 1904, Chalkley was judge of the Augusta and Highland district. Judge Chalkley then moved to Lexington, Kentucky where he was dean of the law school at Kentucky University. From 1907 to 1910, he was dean of the law school at the University of the South in Sewanee. In 1910, Chalkley began teaching law at the University of Kentucky. He retired in 1931. He was also the author of Chronicles of the Scotch-Irish Settlement in Virginia: Extracted from the Original Court Records of Augusta County, 1745-1800. Lyman Chalkley died in Lexington, Kentucky on 21 April 1934 and is buried in Lexington Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1816-1922, of Judge Lyman Chalkley (1861-1934) of Covington and Staunton, Virginia, including correspondence and subject files. The bulk of the collection covers the years 1890-1903. The correspondence is both personal and professional in subject matter. There are many letters written by his wife Eleanor Desha (Breckinridge) Chalkley (1862-1943) while she was in Lexington, Kentucky and Washington, D.C. The subject files include financial records, commonplace and memorandum books, legal notes and suit papers, and other materials.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Correspondence.
II. Subject Files.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1855-1903., Extent: 9 boxes. (Box 1-9)
  The correspondence between 1855 and 1890 is mainly between members of the Jordan family of Powhatan County, Virignia, including Noble Jordan (1801-1882) and his wife Judith Ann (Chappell) Jordan (1810-1881) and their children. The letters to Chalkley begin around 1890, and include many from his wife. Subjects include family news, social activities, loneliness, health, finances, the death of their young son, the legal troubles of her father William Campbell Preston Breckinridge (1837-1904), settling in Covington and Staunton, and purchasing a home. There are also letters from his brother Dr. Charles H. Chalkley (1858-1896), as well as business correspondence with other lawyers and area residents. Topics include administrative and legal matters concerning cases before the court, appointments and elections, financial matters, fraternal and masonic organization business, genealogical research, and regional road issues in Chalkley's capacity as a vice-president of the Virginia State Good Roads Association.
  - 1855. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1858. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1859. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1862. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1863. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1866. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1867. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1868. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1871. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1873. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1874. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1875. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1877-1882. (Box 1, Folder 13-19)
  - 1884-1889. (Box 1, Folder 20-26)
  - 1890 - 1891 (November). (Box 2, Folder 1-15)
  - 1891 (December) - 1892 (August). (Box 3, Folder 1-13)
  - 1892 (September) - 1894 (October). (Box 4, Folder 1-26)
  - 1894 (November) - 1897. (Box 5, Folder 1-20)
  - 1898. (Box 6, Folder 1-10)
  - 1899-1900. (Box 7, Folder 1-16)
  - 1901-1903. (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
  - No Date/Year (Carhart, Martha J.). (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - No Date/Year (Chakley, Charles H.). (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - No Date/Year (Chakley, Eleanor D.). (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
  - No Date/Year (Chakley, Ernest). (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - No Date/Year (Chakley, Lyman). (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - No Date/Year (Chakley, Susan M.). (Box 8, Folder 12-15)
  - No Date/Year (Hall, Anna J.). (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - No Date/Year (Jordan, Alice E.). (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - No Date/Year (Jordan, Henrietta). (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - No Date/Year (Jordan, John O.). (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - No Date/Year (Jordan, Judith Ann). (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - No Date/Year (Jordan, Mary B.). (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - No Date/Year (Miscellaneous). (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1816-1903., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 9-12)
  The subject files contain accounts and receipts, agreements and contracts, bank books, commonplace books of Otway H. Chalkley (1830-1883), genealogical notes on the Jordan and Taylor families, fraternal and masonic materials, insurance papers, legal notes and suit papers, memorandum books, programs, tax receipts, and information on the Virginia State Good Roads Association.
  - 1855. (Box 1, Folder 1)